<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Moderation iustified, and the Lords being at hand emproved, in a sermon at VVestminster before the Honorable House of Commons assembled in Parliament: preached at the late solemne fast, December 25. 1644. By Thomas Thorowgood B. of D. Rector of Grimston in the county of Norfolke: one of the Assembly of Divines. Published by order from that House.</title>
            <author>Thorowgood, Thomas, d. ca. 1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94303</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1069</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E23_6</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860473</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860473</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112593</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94303)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112593)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 4:E23[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Moderation iustified, and the Lords being at hand emproved, in a sermon at VVestminster before the Honorable House of Commons assembled in Parliament: preached at the late solemne fast, December 25. 1644. By Thomas Thorowgood B. of D. Rector of Grimston in the county of Norfolke: one of the Assembly of Divines. Published by order from that House.</title>
                  <author>Thorowgood, Thomas, d. ca. 1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 33, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. L. for Christopher Meredith at the Crane in Pauls Church-yard, and for Thomas Slater at the Swan in Duck-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645[i.e. 1644]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: the 5 in imprint date is crossed out and altered to 1644.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Philippians IV, 5 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112593:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MODERATION
IVSTIFIED, AND
THE LORDS BEING
AT HAND EMPROVED,
IN
A SERMON
AT
VVESTMINSTER
BEFORE THE HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE
HOVSE OF COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MONS
Aſſembled in Parliament:
Preached at the late ſolemne Faſt,
<hi>December</hi> 25. 1644.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Thorowgood</hi> B. of D. Rector of <hi>Grimſton</hi> in the
County of Norfolke: One of the Aſſembly of Divines.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by Order from that Houſe.</p>
            <bibl>Matth. 10. 16.</bibl>
            <q>—Be wiſe as Serpents, and harmeleſſe as Doves.</q>
            <q>Menſura convenit, ne aut nimia remiſſio reddatur aut nimiaa ſeveritas.</q>
            <bibl>Ambros. Offic. lib. 2. cap. 22.</bibl>
            <q>Si quid corrigendum eſt, adhibeatur ea Moderatio, quae Chriſtianos de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceat,
&amp;c.</q>
            <bibl>Eraſm. Epiſt. l. 22. p. 916.</bibl>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed by <hi>I. L.</hi> for <hi>Chriſtopher Meredith</hi> at the Crane in
<hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, and for <hi>Thomas Slater</hi> at the
Swan in Duck-Lane. 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:112593:2"/>
            <head>
               <date>Die Mercurii 25. Decemb. 1644.</date>
            </head>
            <p>IT is this day Ordered by the Commons
Houſe of Parliament, That Maſter <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veningham,</hi>
and Maſter <hi>Liſle,</hi> doe from
this Houſe give thanks to Maſter <hi>Thorowgood,</hi>
and Maſter <hi>Langley,</hi> for the great pains they
took in the Sermons they Preached this day
at the intreaty of this Houſe, at S. <hi>Margarets
Weſtminſter:</hi> (It being the day of Publique
Humiliation) And to deſire them to Print
their Sermons. And it is Ordered, that none
ſhall preſume to Print their, or either of their
Sermons without firſt obtaining libertie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
their hand-writing.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elſyng. Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="appointment_to_print">
            <p>I Doe appoint <hi>Chriſtopher Meredith,</hi> and <hi>Thomas
Slater</hi> to Print this Sermon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THOMAS THOROVVGOOD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:112593:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONORABLE
Houſe of Commons, Aſſembled
in Parliament at Weſtminſter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He thought of coming into that Pulpit
was dreadfull to me, and I did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly
decline it;<note place="margin">1 Sam. 10. 22.</note> 
               <hi>as Saul,</hi> I would
willingly <hi>have hid my ſelfe among
the ſtuffe,</hi> any where rather then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake
the taske.<note place="margin">Palluit ut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> qui preſſit calci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus anguem. Et Juvenal. Sat. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Lugdunenſem
Rhetor dicturus ad aram,</hi> Did Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates
change colour pleading at that Barre? And ſhould
I have no feare being to ſpeake in ſuch a preſence, where ſo
many of you were, and each one reſembled <hi>the children of
a King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 8. 18.</note> 
               <hi>as the Kings of Midian</hi> ſaid to <hi>Gideon,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
of his brethren; yea upon whoſe votes and determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
depends the welfare of three glorious Kingdomes? But
being ſummoned to the ſervice, it was my duty to runne and
prepare my ſelfe, and I found preſently my lot was caſt upon
that very day, which the providence of heaven had deſigned
<pb facs="tcp:112593:3"/>
to fall on Chriſtmas Day,<note place="margin">Gentilet. Exam. p. 206.</note> (as it is named yet) <hi>the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitane
of all the Feſtivities,</hi> ſo <hi>Gaſpar Ferrandi
called it in the Councel of Trent;</hi> It was time for me
then by conſideration, recollection, and other thoughts to
<hi>caſt out feare;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 4. 8.</note> and for my animation, the alluſion of him to
<hi>Caeſar</hi> happily occurred, as they that dare confidently ſpeake
in your judicious and formidable Aſſemblie, conſider not
what <hi>Conſtellations</hi> you are, nor of what <hi>Magnitude;</hi>
ſo thoſe, that deſpondingly be afraid, are ignorant of your
benigne <hi>Aſpects,</hi> and gracious <hi>Influences.</hi> The election
of a <hi>Theme,</hi> and the manner of handling it was in my
power, and by Divine guidance I choſe <hi>Moderation,</hi> not
becauſe you wanted it, but for that ſome ſo ſuppoſed, and I
ſaw, even that <hi>Chriſtian grace,</hi> well underſtood would ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie
your proceedings: Your eares entertained the Diſcourſe
with ſpontaneous attention, with the vertue of the Text,
which <hi>Tertullus</hi> beg'd of <hi>Felix,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 24. 4.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. you have now
required it to the other ſenſe, to another cenſure, <hi>in publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum
formidandumque judicium</hi> as <hi>Caſſiane</hi> ſaid upon
his like occaſion;<note place="margin">De Incarnat. praefat.</note> and for my part,<note place="margin">Pro captu Lectoris habent ſua fata libelli.</note> though the ſubject mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
I know, will meet with fatall judgings, and my weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes
alſo be ever before me, yet I have obeyed your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,
and with the exoptation of <hi>Oroſius</hi> to <hi>Auſtin, Uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam
tam efficaciter quam libenter:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Praefat. Hiſt.</note> for now, as <hi>Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations</hi>
have beene made to you of <hi>Zeale, Righteouſneſſe,
Magnanimitie, Perſeverance, &amp;c.</hi> ſo the world ſhall ſee
you <hi>Patrons of Moderation alſo,</hi> notwithstanding the
<hi>unpolitique, Antichriſtian,</hi> and <hi>Tyrannicall</hi> endevours
of your <hi>Oppoſites,</hi> ſome of which laboured ſo much ſome
yeares ſince to embroyle the Nation againſt <hi>Scotland,</hi> in ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconciliable
and inteſtine combuſtions, the perfect uniting
of whom to <hi>ENGLAND</hi> was the zealous induſtrie of the
<pb facs="tcp:112593:3"/>
wiſeſt <hi>Patriots</hi> in former times, as our Chronicles re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,
and who now alſo, by ſupernaturall providence, in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,
and many other obligations, are contrived into a
more firme accord then ever. Thoſe other horrid Miſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants
of <hi>Ireland</hi> have raked <hi>Hell</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> for the inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
and exerciſes of ſuch cruel barbarities upon our miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
brethren,<note place="margin">King <hi>Charles</hi> Declarat. with the advice of his Privie Counſell.</note> 
               <hi>that no Chriſtian eare can heare with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
horrour, nor Story parallel, as his Majeſtie did
declare againſt thoſe barbarous Rebels.</hi> I wiſh that
<hi>Remonſtrance</hi> of our Clergie there were commanded to be
in every Pariſh of <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> and the <hi>additionall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions</hi>
haſtened to the Preſſe, that all the good people of
the Land might know their good meaning to them: And in
this Kingdome there was a generation of <hi>New Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi>
that paved the way to Popery, and under the colour of
<hi>a good worke in hand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Holy Table, Name, and Thing, <hi>p. 2. p. 192. p.</hi> 204.</note> 
               <hi>and the pietie of the times were
buſied in taking the out-workes, and that being done
they would have a bout with the Fort it ſelfe:</hi> It is the
language and ſentence of him that here may well be credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
and our eyes ſaw then, the Innovations ſo numerous,
that with a little time and obſervation it might be demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated,
the lawleſſe <hi>Mutation</hi> even then was greater from
the rules, and received practiſe, then it is like to be by the
<hi>Directory</hi> ſo much expected, which beſide <hi>Parliament</hi>
Authoritie, will have the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and the example of
<hi>Reformed Churches</hi> to give it countenance; I thought in
this Epiſtle I might make ſome further mentioning, but I
muſt remember that of <hi>Auſtin</hi> to <hi>Macedonius, Negotio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſſimos
in Republica viros,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ep. 54. Init.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; non ſuis, ſed aliorum
utilitatibus attentiſſimos non debemus occupare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oemio:</hi>
I will turne therefore my prefacing, into praying,
that our <hi>God onely wiſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 16. 27.</note> would fill every one of you with
<pb facs="tcp:112593:4"/>
               <hi>wiſedome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 3. 17.</note> 
               <hi>even that wiſdome which is from above,
and is firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the
grace of the Text,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ruth 4. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Moderate, and full of good fruits,</hi>
that gaſping <hi>Ireland</hi> may be recovered by you, and as you
have <hi>done worthily</hi> for <hi>Scotland,</hi> you may be <hi>famous</hi> in
<hi>ENGLAND,</hi> and regaining the <hi>Kings royall Perſon and
favour,</hi> you may make him glorious alſo, and <hi>raiſe up</hi> in his
Dominions <hi>the foundations for many generations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 58. 12.</note> 
               <hi>and
be called the Repairers of the breaches, the Reſtorers
of the paths to dwell in.</hi> I ſhall waite the complement
of Gods good providence in you, and by you, that in his due
ſeaſon every <hi>mountaine</hi> of oppoſition may be a <hi>plaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 4. 7.</note> and
theſe <hi>troublous times</hi> may determine in the readvance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Dan. 9. 25.</note>
and firme eſtabliſhing of Righteouſneſſe and Peace,
through your hands; which is, and ſhall be in the dayly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion
of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your conſtant Oratour at
the Throne of Grace,
THOMAS THOROVVGOOD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112593:4"/>
            <head>A
Sermon preached before the Honourable
Houſe of COMMONS, at the Monethly Faſt,
<date>December 25. 1644.</date>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Phil. 4. verſ. 5.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
Let your moderation be known unto all men, the Lord
is at hand.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is Gods word that I have read, let no
mans zeale be hot againſt it, or me; and
how meet it is for this time, this very
time, judge not till you have heard: my
thoughts were not faſtened here with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
ſome difficultie, I conſidered again
and again, and as often prayed, that I
might ſpeake a word in ſeaſon; it muſt
be affirmed, there is all the reaſon in the world, you be even
now alſo incited to zeale, wiſdome, magnanimitie, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
reſolution, but <hi>incluſivè,</hi> there is no Chriſtian grace, I
know,<note place="margin">Eph. 4. 15.</note> but you would be acquainted with it,<note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> and <hi>grow up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
Chriſt in all things, and be eſtabliſhed in every good word and
worke.</hi> But that I may in time take off all prejudice, I ſhall
not ſpeake of <hi>Moderation</hi> in the ſenſe of Politians and the
world, but as it is a Chriſtian grace, and not inconſiſtent with
holy zeal, they were both in our Maſter Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 1. we
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:112593:5"/>
read it,<note place="margin">Joh. 2. 17. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>gentleneſſe of Chriſt,</hi> and my <hi>Philippians</hi> had to doe
with <hi>dogs, evill workers, dangerous men of the conciſion,</hi> Chap.
3. verſ. 2. yea, verſ. 18, 19. <hi>With wicked walkers, of whom he
could not ſpeake without weeping, enemies of the croſſe of Chriſt,
belly gods, muck-wormes, minding earthly things,</hi> lively cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters
of a great part of your oppoſites: and if Saint <hi>Paul</hi>
then, ſurely, I may ſay now, <hi>Let your moderation be known un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
all men, the Lord is at hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If yet to any apprehenſion the firſt clauſe ſeeme a cooler,
the ſecond will ſhew, it ſeemes ſo onely, and my <hi>Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
doth not make a medley of Religion, nor complyes with
any tranſgreſſion, but it is a bleſſed, and a watchfull vertue,
living alwayes in Gods ſight, and in expectation of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
to come; it quencheth no mans zeale, onely it makes
it burne faire, and ſhine more cleare; it is enjoyned in the firſt
clauſe of the Text, and the reaſon thereof is in the latter, <hi>the
Lord is at hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the former we have theſe foure things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The grace required, <hi>Moderation.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The ſeat or ſubject of it, <hi>your, of you.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. Its declaration and diſcovery, <hi>let it be known.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. The ampliation and extent, <hi>to all men.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The ſecond clauſe ſhall be touched upon as a reaſon, but my
purpoſe is, God willing, to handle both in that method, which
our dayes have found ſo happy, by Doctrine and Vſe, yet in
the explication, and application, I ſhall paſſe thorough each
particular.</p>
            <p>Let this then be the firſt Doctrine,<note place="margin">Doctrin 1.</note> 
               <hi>Moderation is a catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
grace of univerſall practiſe by all men to all men:</hi> and the
Application will fall into five particulars, <hi>words of Complaint,
Limitation, Conſutation, Inſtruction,</hi> and <hi>Exhortation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Doctrine of the <hi>Lords being at hand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2.</note> will from
the Scriptures hold forth unto us theſe ſeven ſeaſonable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations,
fitted for our preſent practiſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Speedy Repentance from dead works.</item>
               <item>2. Wiſe weaning our ſelves from the world.</item>
               <item>3. Conſtant perſeverance in true Religion.</item>
               <item>4. Zealous endeavour after holineſſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:112593:5"/>
5. Chriſtian patience in tribulation.</item>
               <item>6. Holy faith in the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</item>
               <item>7. Sober watchfulneſſe unto prayer.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Moderation is a catholique grace of univerſall practiſe by
all men to all men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doctrin. 1.</note> In the Originall, it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Adjectively;
which is ſometimes emphaticall, in the proprietie of the
language; but that criticiſme, and curioſitie ſhall be omitted,
yet it is fit to mention the different interpretation.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Theophylact. Haimo, Lyra, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Modeſty,</hi> ſo it is read by ſome, which is a vertue,
keeping ſuch mediocritie in externall things, that no mans
eye, or conſcience is offended, it moderates the outward
converſe in ſpeech,<note place="margin">Aquin. 22. 120. 2, 3.</note> apparell, and life, in their ſenſe, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre
it to the words immediately foregoing, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 4. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce,
&amp;c. So <hi>Bernard, We reioyce in that we hope, becauſe the
Lord is at hand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">T. 1. p. 178.</note> 
               <hi>we reioyce in that we ſuffer, that our Modeſty
might be known to all men:</hi> this <hi>modeſty</hi> is not the maidens
bluſh onely, but a colour well becoming men, women, all
that be Chriſtians; nature puts a modeſt aſpect upon thoſe
that ſhame to doe evill, the blood making haſt, as it were, to
cover even the ſuſpition of guilt,<note place="margin">Offic. l. 1. c. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> extends it to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures,
gate, and bodily motion, telling his own experiment
this way, how he refuſed to admit one into Orders, meerely
for his immodeſt geſture; he ſuffered not another Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
to walke before him, his going was ſo offenſive, and
uncomely: and I was deceived, ſaith he, in neither, the one
ran out of his function, the other out of his Religion, and
turned Arrian, ſo diſcernable is the inward man ſometimes
by the motion of the outward: no marvell therefore if light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
of geſture be immodeſty and a prohibited evill, <hi>Prov.</hi>
6. 13. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 3. 16. Some better Expoſiters read it,</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Genoven. Fulk. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Patient minde;</hi> and ſo our own Tranſlators elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where
Engliſh the word, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 3. and thus it is a dutie
very ſeaſonable for theſe ſuffering times, when men can be as
the Turtle,<note place="margin">Pier. Hierogl.</note> though in ſeverall conditions, have but one note,
keep the ſame tune, when they be quiet in tribulation, and
murmure not when affliction comes; but the laſt clauſe of the
Text will invite us to patience by and by.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ſhall inſiſt therefore upon our own reading. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:112593:6"/>
which is allowed by all Reformed Divines that I
have ſeene,<note place="margin">Clvin, Beza, Zanch. &amp;c. Illyr. Clav. Scr. Modeſtia.</note> one onely excepted, who in ſome other things
alſo is himſelfe excepted againſt. And <hi>Moderation</hi> is a word
of ſuch latitude, that it reacheth to publique employments,
in civill matters,<note place="margin">Zanch. &amp;c.</note> in the judgement of thoſe that well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
the force of it; thence they call Moderation the Aſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor
of Iuſtice, mollifying the rigour, and ſeverity of the law,
for Legiſtators intend ſtrictneſſe of rule, but their provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
not being infinite, nor able to foreſee all occurrences,
leave a neceſſitie for <hi>Moderation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aquin. 22. 120. 10.</note> and Writers of both Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions
doe thus inſtance,<note place="margin">Antonin. S. 4. 5. 19.</note> it is juſt <hi>depoſitum reddere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zanch. in Phil.</note> It is hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty
and faithfulneſſe to reſtore the pledge, or that we are truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
with, yet ſometimes, ſay they, it is not iniquitie but <hi>Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi>
to doe otherwiſe: for example, a man hath given ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
his ſword to keepe, he proves furious and diſtempered,
the other is not bound to reſtore the ſword, becauſe he may
abuſe it to his own, or others hurt; <hi>Vel, cum quis depoſitum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſcit
ad impugnationem patriae,</hi> Thus, to take away a mans
goods or lands is injuſtice, yet if it be done indeed for the
Commonweale, it is <hi>Moderation,</hi> not iniquitie: For the well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare
of the naturall body diet is abated, though the patient be
unwilling, ſleep is denyed, blood is let out, yea a member is
cut off for the preſervation of the whole; and for the ſafetie
of the body politique, we may without wrong be drawn to
part w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> our private for the publique good, <hi>Intereſt Reipublicae
ut re ſua quiſque bene utatur.</hi> This <hi>Moderation</hi> is the ſoul and
life of the law, without which the law it ſelfe ſometime will
ſavour of unrighteouſneſſe. This may ſeeme a paradox, and it
is indeed <hi>miraculum Iuriſtarum</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. c. p. 94.</note> 
               <hi>quia diſcedit à regula,</hi>
ſaith <hi>Luther,</hi> a ſtrange thing to tranſgreſſe a Rule without
tranſgreſſion: and this ſerves much to juſtifie the preſent
proceedings, and might ſatisfie the diſaffected alſo, if reaſon
could doe it, in ſuch times as theſe, which they have helped
our ſinnes to bring upon us: it is not injuſtice, much leſſe cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie,
to raiſe forces, require contributions, impoſe taxations
for the ſafetie of the kingdome;<note place="margin">Aquin. &amp; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonin. ubi ſupar.</note> and two of the forenamed
Writers give this rule, it is good ſometime, to paſſe by the
words of the law, and follow that which reaſon calles for,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112593:6"/>
and the common benefit. I ſhall touch upon Moderation again,
as it reflects upon publique affaires, now therefore I ſpeake of
it, as it hath reference to private Chriſtians. Some will have the
word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, over and above that which is right and
juſt; others,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> either from a Noune that ſignifies equall and good, or
a Verbe that is to yeeld, the Prepoſition adding further force,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and
then it is a vertue inciting good men ſo much to right and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
that for its promotion they yeeld ſometimes, and part with
their own. Further, it ſtops the violence of a mans own paſſions,
guiding them to their due ends,<note place="margin">Pier.</note> therefore in the Hieroglyphick
the Bridle &amp; Helme are the Emblemes of <hi>Moderation;</hi> and in this
ſenſe it is a prime and choiſe vertue, carrying a man to the top of
the hill, moralitie cannot get higher, and many Chriſtians come
ſhort thereof, both in themſelves, and to others. And yet further, it
is a grace ſhining outwardly, it is viſible, and illuſtrious, <hi>known un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
men,</hi> it hath influence into all other vertues, it qualifies and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers
them, it is as ſalt that makes other things ſavory, they reliſh
not ſo well without the ſalt of <hi>Moderation,</hi> it is the graine that
evens the ſcale, aequipoyſeth all, it curbs exceſſes, ſupplies defects,
and is every way helpfull; the moſt zealous would be loath to
heare, as thoſe, <hi>Rom. 10. 2. They have a zeale of God, but not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to knowledge,</hi> the zeale according to knowledge is the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration</hi>
commended, commanded in the Text: and as in Schooles
and taking up of differences the Vmpire, and Moderator under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands,
<hi>pro &amp; con,</hi> the allegations of either ſide, by his wiſdome
he is able to remove ſcruples, and give every one their due; ſo this
<hi>Moderation</hi> is the <hi>medium,</hi> makes the vertue, walkes as it were
betwixt the two extreames, and keeps off the diſtempers of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
as <hi>Matth. 10. 16. Be wiſe as ſerpents, and harmleſſe as doves,</hi>
this <hi>Moderation</hi> regulates the rigour of the one, and the ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
of the other, ſtanding up to keepe out both venome and folly,
that wrong be neither done, nor revenged. And yet neerer, in
our converſe with men, this <hi>Moderation</hi> hath chiefe place, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding
us to be fierce in reaſoning, raſh in cenſuring, not ſtand too
ſtrictly upon our termes, but in our defence and vindication abate
our right, part with our own, yeeld to our neighbours, interpret
fairely their ſayings, and doings, and make the beſt conſtructions
we can, that our <hi>Moderation may be known,</hi> &amp;c. It is in <hi>Beza's</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112593:7"/>
               <hi>a quiet ſpirit taking all in good part,</hi> and I may call it a
gracious minde that thinks and ſpeaks well of all, and doth ill
to none.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It regulates thoſe evill humors, that be ſo riſe in nature,
even <hi>debates, envyings, wrath, ſtrifes, backbitings, whiſperings, ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings,
tumults,</hi> which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was ſo much afraid, he ſhould
finde among his Corinthians, 2 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 12. 20. and thus <hi>Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
is nigh of kinne to Chriſtian charitie, it is not apt to credit ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours,
or be miſguided by reports, <hi>it is not puffed up, doth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have
it ſelfe unſeemely, thinketh not evill,</hi> &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 4, 5, 6, 7. it
will have full information before it paſſe ſentence ſo much as in
its own breaſt againſt any, ſhe will follow her Lords example, who
though the cry of Sodome was great, yet for our inſtruction he
ſaid, <hi>I will goe downe now, and ſee, whether they have done altogether
according to the cry,</hi> &amp;c. Gen. 18. 21. and though the appearance
be foule, our thoughts and ſpeeches muſt be as faire as they may;
<hi>Ioſeph</hi> thus <hi>moderated</hi> the ſorrow of his brethren for their ſelling
him into <hi>Egypt, God,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſent me before you, to ſave your lives
by a mig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ie deliverance.</hi> Gen. 45. 7. and is it not conſiderable, that
though <hi>Solomon</hi> had then taken to himſelfe ſo many wives and
concubines, which in a great meaſure alſo tooke away his heart,
yet the holy Ghoſt uſeth this expreſſion, <hi>Solomon did evill in the
ſight of the Lord, and went not fully after the Lord, as did David his
father?</hi> 1 Kings 11. 6. ſee and learne the language of Canaan; <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration,</hi>
teacheth to aſcribe many offences to ignorance and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie:
Thus our Saviour Chriſt prayeth for his crucifiers,<note place="margin">Facinus enorrae ignorantus tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit, non ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae Theophylact. in lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Luk.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doroth. Doct. 16.</note>
23. 34. <hi>Father, forgive them, for they know not what they doe;</hi> and
Saint <hi>Peter</hi> learned this <hi>Moderation</hi> from his Maſter, <hi>Act.</hi> 3. 17.
<hi>I wot that through ignorance ye did it, as did alſo your rulers:</hi> As
that holy man judged one brothers ſoule to be very pure, becauſe
his cell was ſo trim, and he ſaid, another was very righteous with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
that tooke ſo little care of externall neatneſſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Moderation is a well-doing grace, ſo good, that it
doth ill to none, ſhe knows, that even nature did ever account de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
of revenge a feminine and cowardly paſſion: and that is but
an emptie objection, with which nevertheleſſe ſome mens
mouthes are filled, he is a ſilly fellow, hath no mettall in him, that
is inſenſible of affronts, but that coine of revenge what mettall is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112593:7"/>
it made of? its ſtamp and allowance, I am ſure, is not from heaven,
it is digged from the mines of hell, by the hands of fleſh, and bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
the image, impreſſe, and ſuperſcription of the world, the fleſh,
and the devill,—<hi>it is earthly, ſenſuall and devilliſh,</hi> Iam. 3. 15.
You ſee then the low deſcent, the baſe pedegree of this lofty va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour;
but our <hi>Moderation</hi> is better borne, even from above, and
hath learned of her Maſter Chriſt, to be friendly to thoſe that be
hoſtile, <hi>Matth. 5. 44. Love your enemies, bleſſe them that curſe
you,</hi> though they revile, we muſt not, <hi>doe good to them that hate
you, &amp;c.</hi> though by word and action they damnifie us, we muſt
ſtudy to winne them by our well-doing; and <hi>this is the good turne,</hi>
ſaith father <hi>Latimer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Part 2. p. 57.</note> 
               <hi>our Maſter Chriſt allowes us to doe to our
enemies, to Warme them at our fire,</hi> and draw them from evill by
our good: It were eaſie to expatiate here, and enlarge ſeverall
reaſons: as</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Reaſons.</note> 
               <hi>Moderation</hi> is a gracious and an acceptable vertue, it
ſweetens and endeares the owner thereof, whereever he comes,
it offers a kind of violence upon mens affections bofore they be
aware: <hi>as the unbeleeving husband is wonne by the holy converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the wife,</hi> 1 Pet. 3. 1.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is an healthfull vertue: immoderation and <hi>wrath
killeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de C. D. Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ot<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Iob 52. As <hi>Sylla</hi> is ſaid in his anger to break a veine,
of which Rupture he died; but, <hi>qui ſuavis eſt vivit in moderationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi>
Pro. 12. 12. It is not indeed in the Hebrew, but the Seventie,
and Latine ſo have it; and Interpreters thereupon ſay, That life is
preſerved and prolonged by <hi>Moderation:</hi> but,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, take the reaſon of the Text, in that ſenſe of it, <hi>the Lord
is at hand,</hi> ſeeing, and hearing, all our cogitations and ſpeeches,
<hi>Pſal. 129. 2, 3, 4. Thou knoweſt my downſuting, &amp;c. thou under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeſt
my thoughts afar off, &amp;c. there is not a word in my tongue,
but loe, thou O Lord, knoweſt it altogether.</hi> It was good counſell
of <hi>Seneca, Sic fac omnia, tanquam ſpectet aliquis;</hi> and <hi>Moderation</hi>
is not to learne, that God himſelfe alwaies obſerveth the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
and commotions of our ſpirits, and every other diſtemper.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>The Lord is at hand,</hi> to call us to account for every
inward and outward exorbitance, thinke, ſpeake well of all, doe
ill to none; if we have beene immoderate in this or any other way,
let us repent, amend, and remember <hi>the Lord is at hand</hi> to reckon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112593:8"/>
with us for every miſdemeanour. I might proceed in further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation,
and declare that this Moderation is of ſuch vaſt, and
comprehenſive extent that it checks all overflowings of heart,
tongue, geſture, apparell, diet; yea it hath influence upon all our
doings and ſufferings: and then the</p>
            <p>Firſt Vſe will be matter of <hi>complaint</hi> in the univerſall want of
this <hi>Moderation</hi> almoſt in all things and perſons,<note place="margin">Application. Vſe 1.</note> in this age, and
inundation of miſery; no <hi>Moderation</hi> or abatement of mirth;
though all the Land mourne, how few doe lay it to heart? as
much exceſſe in diet almoſt as ever, when ſo many be ready to
ſterve; pride, and thoſe other abominable vanities now notorious
alſo, even women, wont to be the devout Sex, yet now how are
ſome of them <hi>ſpots in your feaſts,</hi> Iude 14. with ſpots in their
faces, as if they would out-face our very dayes of Humiliation;
and men, how greedy are they of the world, plotting and proje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting
for riches and places, as if here were their <hi>abiding citie,</hi> and
they had no thought of one to come? and in Civill matters, thoſe
Courts and contentions, I heare not that men find either much
more equitie or expedition.</p>
            <p>Second Vſe of <hi>limitation;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vſe 2.</note> for it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it muſt be
<hi>of you; your moderation,</hi> not <hi>of, or in things</hi> belonging unto God,
it reacheth not to the principles or practiſe of Religion; obſerve
that once for all; Men muſt be as zealous for truth and holineſſe as
they can; Men, all men have no power to be Moderatours of
them, themſelves are bounded, and confined by the Almighty,
as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid to <hi>Shimei: Build thee an houſe at Ieruſalem, goe
not from thence any whither,</hi> 1 King 2. 36, 37. <hi>From Gods word
nothing muſt be taken, and nothing muſt be added to it,</hi> Deut. 4. 2.
12. 32. <hi>Revel.</hi> 22. 18. Our God is omniſcient, diſcerning at
firſt all poſſible emergencies of things, perſons, and occurſions;
ſo his Statutes be perfect and abſolute, and muſt be obeyed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
diſpute or moderation; it is a moſt dangerous adventure, to
examine, or regulate Divine Truths by Humane wiſdome; ſuch
daring hath introduced many foule Errors into the Church, and
retained them: our Maſter Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Drinke ye all of this,</hi> Matth.
26. 27. All the Clergie, ſay the men of <hi>Rome,</hi> the bloud may
hang on Lay-mens beards, they may ſpill it on the ground: our
God commands all men to know his Word and will; the Papiſts
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112593:8"/>
will needs be Moderators here, and forbiddeth Scriptures in the
Mother Tongue, becauſe the common people may profane and
abuſe them: a ſeeming antinomy and oppoſition appears ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
in the Word of God; yet even there and then men ought
not to moderate, but one Text muſt be compared with another,
and ſo darke places will be enlightened; In every doubtfull buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
they were wont to <hi>aske of the Lord,</hi> Gen. 25. 22. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi>
23. and elſewhere; <hi>or of his Prieſts,</hi> Exod. 18. 15. <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. 9.
<hi>alibique;</hi> or <hi>at his word,</hi> 1 Sam. 22. 5. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 18. 4. and in other
places; we muſt ſay with Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in all ſuch matters, <hi>What
ſaith the Scripture?</hi> Rom. 4. 3. And againe, <hi>what ſaith the Scripture?</hi>
Galat. 4. 30. The Scripture is the ſole rule, judge, and moderator.
The firſt Chriſtians were exceedingly preciſe this way; not to
tell you how they would not part with a word, not a ſyllable, not
a letter in divine truths; they complied not with the Heathen in
ſmall matters:<note place="margin">Optat. l. 3. p. 71. Plin. Ep. 97. Tertul. de Cor. Mil. p. 153. Id. p. 283. Suidas in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Euſeb. Hiſt. l. 4. c. 15. m p. 180.</note> 
               <hi>They would not burne incenſe, nor weare a crowne,
nor ſtick their doores with Laurel, nor lay grapes at Bacchus feet;
Polycarpe would rather dye then ſweare by Caeſars fortune; and
the Chriſtians in Iuſtine Martyr would not tell a lie to ſave their
lives:</hi> the after connivence and complication brought in errors
by heapes, and huddles: and <hi>Rhenanus</hi> a learned Papiſt confeſſeth
the foundation thereof was laid in this preſumed <hi>Moderation:
the firſt approaches of Gentiles to Chriſtianity were invited and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained
with ſome pleaſing changes of their rites; whereas their
totall resection would have thruſt them quite off:</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Tertul. p. 103. M.</note> but thoſe tolerable
alterations as they ſeemed, introduced moſt intolerable ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition,
and profaneneſſe, the ſmart whereof doth yet remaine;
and we are not purged from the ſhame, and ſtaine of it to this
very day; there ought to have beene no blinding, no blending in
Divine Truths; Men ſhould not bring their mixtures hither: <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
this now to thy governour, and will he be pleaſed with thee?</hi> Mal.
1. 8. We will not have droſſe with our ſilver, nor mingle vinegar
with wine; we muſt ſay here as <hi>Iehu</hi> to <hi>Iehonadab, Come ſee my
zeale,</hi> 2 King. 10. 16. And you muſt be moſt earneſt againſt
thoſe errors that be likelieſt to encroach; and even Chriſtian <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration</hi>
will grow warme againſt the ſtreame of common cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption:
Our Maſter Chriſt forbad expreſſely, to <hi>ſweare by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
or by earth, or by Ieruſalem, &amp;c.</hi> Matth. 5. 34, &amp;c. For it
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112593:9"/>
ſeemes by <hi>Philo</hi> the Iew,<note place="margin">m. p. 490.</note> that was the cuſtomary ſinne of thoſe
times: and ſo, <hi>Gal. 1. 4. Chriſt hath delivered us from the preſent
evill world.</hi> There is an Emphaſis in that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the
preſent evill world: we muſt be moſt watchfull againſt thoſe
corruptions, in faith, and manners, that are growing upon us,
what ever they be; and not to ſpeake of others now, for my part,
uſe what <hi>Moderation</hi> you pleaſe to the perſons, and eſtates of the
Papiſts; but let us avoid, I beſeech you, whatſoever in truth, or
true appearance is doctrinally ſo: the Iudaicall Rites had another
kind of claime, yet the firſt Chriſtians declined them with great
and univerſall vehemency: <hi>Say the world what it will, I freely
pronounce,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. T. 2. ep. p. 346.</note> ſaith Hierome, <hi>that the Ceremonies of the Iewes are
pernicious and deadly to Christians; and whoſoever obſerves them,
whether he be Iew or Gentile is ſunke downe into hell:</hi> and yet Gods
direction to his firſt people concernes all his Iſrael now, <hi>Levit.</hi>
18. 3. <hi>After the doings of the Land of Egypt wherein ye dwelt ſhall
ye not doe, and after the doings of the Land of Canaan, whither I
bring you, ſhall ye not doe, &amp;c.</hi> And in both reſpects we ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon
the waies of Popery, for we came halting from them, and
they yet dwell among us; we have found by too long, and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
and wounding experience, all our complying with them
could not winne the leaſt upon them. In our firſt Reformation
Archbiſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi> enjoyned <hi>that no Miniſter ſhould order mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
ſo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Injunct. 3.</note> 
               <hi>that the unlearned people thinke the old Popiſh Maſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues
ſtill;</hi> but the <hi>piety of our times,</hi> as it <hi>was called,</hi> wanted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
but a command, to trimme the Sacraments of Chriſt after
the plaine Popiſh dreſſe of Antichriſt. In our ſecond Reformation
a Biſhop printed it,<note place="margin">Bp. of Dur. <hi>Anno</hi> 1561.</note> in the beginning of the Queenes reigne; <hi>we
are but too much like the Papiſts, that is our fault generally, that we
differ not more from them;</hi> but <hi>the good worke in hand of late,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted
it th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir great honour and glory to come nigh unto them:
To conclude, and I know you obſerve it well, danger from <hi>Rome</hi>
was foreſene in the firſt, and ſecond Reformation; I ſay no more,
but, <hi>Beware the third time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third Vſe of Confutation:<note place="margin">Vſe 3.</note> it is of the Remonſtrants, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians,
and Socinians, who endevour from my Text, to get
countenance for the Babyloniſh Errour, the allowance of all Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,
as if, becauſe the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Let your moderation be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112593:9"/>
knowne unto all men;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Remonſtranst. ſect. ult. Cenſur. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſt. Praef. Harm. Remonſt. &amp; Socin. p. 231.</note> therefore all mens conceits muſt be borne
with in Religion, and every one ſuffered in what he ſuppoſeth
to be truth: it is a cunning and couſening deviſe, that ſtrikes in
with corrupt nature; but becauſe it offers violence to my Text, I
cannot be true to it, or you, if ſomewhat be not added by way of
vindication, and it will be in theſe ſixe particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Is it probable that our Apoſtle, who elſewhere, almoſt
every where, is ſo zealous for unitie, againſt Schiſmes, ſhould in
any ſort tolerate them, and ſo voluntarily open a wide door<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
for diviſion? in this very Epiſtle he writes for peace, even paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionately,
but with mightie power, <hi>Phil 2. 1, 2. If there be any
conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of love, if any fellowſhip of the
ſpirit, if any bowels and mercies, fulfill ye my ioy, that ye be like
minded, having the ſame love, being of one accord, and of one mind.</hi>
And in the next <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. 16.—<hi>Let us walke by the ſame rule,
let us mind the ſame thing:</hi> expreſſions different from all licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
tolerations: the ſame Apoſtle abounds in ſerious dehorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
from <hi>ſchiſmes and diſſentions,</hi> Rom 13. 12. 16. 17. and <hi>as car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,</hi>
1 Cor, 3. 3. and in other places: And he doth very often ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort
with earneſt words and arguments, not onely that we <hi>be like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded,</hi>
Rom. 15. 6. <hi>Phil. 2. 2. and of one mind,</hi> 2 Cor. 13. 11. <hi>but
of the ſame mind,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 1 Cor. 10. 10. <hi>ioyned, yea ioynted together in the
ſame mind, and in the ſame iudgement:</hi> And is here the leaſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation
of that multiplying Doctrine? neither will that excuſe,
ſo long as they all breath Chriſt, tend to the advancement of Chriſt;
it matters not: but let Saint <hi>Paul</hi> anſwer this Objection alſo, <hi>Is
Chriſt divided?</hi> 1 Cor. 1. 13. Conſider it well, and ſeaſon your
conſideration with that of our Maſter Chriſt himſelfe, <hi>Mar.</hi> 9. 50.
<hi>Have ſalt in your ſelves, and have peace one with another:</hi> If we
were preſerved by humilitie from the corruptions of ſelfe-opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
it would be no hard matter to embrace unitie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Such allowance would prove deſtructive to holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
both perſonall, and domeſticall; <hi>Omnis religio, &amp; nulla re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligio,</hi>
would ſoone be the ſame: Suppoſe the husband of one
opinion, the wife of another, the children, it may be, of one or
two other,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and the ſervants of as many more; what ſhall the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
of the houſe doe here? how performe the family duties?
diverſitie of opinions, like ſo many <hi>hatchets interrupting their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112593:10"/>
prayers,</hi> 1 Pet. 3. 7. <hi>chopping all devotion and piety in pieces:</hi> as the
Duke of <hi>Wittenberge</hi> was wont to ſay, New garments introduce
new manners, new manners bring in new men, and new men
thruſt out the old; ſo new opinions ſuffered will devoure the
old; and the toleration of every Religion, will deſtroy all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion:
and in concluſion, leave no Religion at all.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, this libertie is inconſiſtent with civill tranquillitie; the
bleeding condition of our owne Nation at preſent is a living, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
a dying witneſſe of this; and if that one Religion of Popery
ſo tolerated as it was, hath brought in upon us ſo many deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;
what will that multiplication doe, but haſten deſolation
without recovery? for every party would endevour to ſupport
it ſelfe to the prejudice of the reſt; <hi>&amp; dum de religione certatum
eſt regio, dum de caelo terra amiſſa;</hi> as it was ſaid long ſince.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the late Biſhops of <hi>Ireland</hi> may put this libertie to
to ſilence and ſhame; for when not long ſince a toleration of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery
in that Kingdome was propoſed, they ſaid, To give the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts
a toleration is a grievous ſinne, and will make us acceſſary to
all their abominations, and the perdition alſo of ſeduced ſoules.</p>
            <p>Fifthly,<note place="margin">Cam. op. ſucciſ. part. 1. p. 262.</note> This may be currant doctrine among the Turks; and
the Grand Signior told his Mufti, that is, his chiefe Prieſt, As a
Garden is beautified with varietie of flowers, ſo his Empire
would be adorned with diverſities of religion: let ſuch tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
find allowance in the Turks Paradiſe; it ſhall never, I truſt,
be planted in the Paradiſe of God.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, We have undertaken all in the Nationall Covenant,
the eſtabliſhment of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformitie,</hi> and how that can ſtand with
this <hi>Omniformitie,</hi> indeed <hi>Nulliformitie,</hi> I underſtand not: it was
a prodigious thing in the dayes of <hi>Ieremiah</hi> the Prophet, <hi>Ier.</hi> 2. 28.
<hi>According to the number of thy cities, are thy Gods, O Iudah:</hi> here
would ſoon appeare another kind of multiplying and increaſe; but
though this fancy be never ſo plauſible, Divine providence hath
ſhut it out of our Campe by our Covenant.</p>
            <p>Fourth Vſe of Inſtruction;<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe 4.</note> If our <hi>Moderation muſt be knowne
unto all men,</hi> in ſome caſes then it is not unlawfull to cauſe our
light to ſhine, not purpoſely, proclaiming our righteouſneſſe in
the Market, or ſounding a Trumpet; but firſt, a man may be his
owne Encomiaſt, if his innocency be ſuſpected, or beſmeared;
thus did <hi>Samuel,</hi> 1 Sam. 12. 3.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:112593:10"/>
Secondly, if a Preachers doctrine be traduced, he may make his
own Apologie, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did, <hi>Act.</hi> 22. 1.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, By the ſame example, a man may ſtirre up others to
emulation, by magnifying his office, ſo we read, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 13.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Thus it is ſaid, if a man be tempted to deſpaire, it is
wiſdome to remember good actions paſt, as <hi>Iob,</hi> when he was
ſtaggered by the reproaches of his friends, thought of his former
integritie, which kept him ſtanding; and I have read of another,
that in his tentations to pride, objected his ſinne againſt himſelfe,
which brought him to humiliation, and in his fits of deſpaire he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected
upon his righteouſneſſe, and was ſo preſerved from falling:
and <hi>Moderation</hi> muſt not be known for pompe and oſtentation;
<hi>Plus laborandam eſt celare virtutes quam vitia;</hi> It is not ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
to hide our vertues, as our vices; the revealing even of
piety may be ſinne, but the confeſſion of ſinne is pietie; and if a
mans righteous performances be occaſionally divulged, God muſt
have the praiſe for it, who is the donour of it: Like veſſels of gold
and ſilver, that receive not into them the Sun-ſhining ſplendour,
but by reverberation returne it whence it came, ſo doe the Saints
in all their gifts and graces, well called in our language gifts, that
nothing be aſſumed unto man, but all aſcribed to Chriſt, <hi>the King
of Saints, Revel.</hi> 15. 3. from whom proceedeth every good and
perfect gift, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1. 17.</p>
            <p>Fifth Vſe of Exhortation,<note place="margin">Vſe 5. 1.</note> will ſpeake as it is of private and
publique concernment, and firſt, <hi>A ſenſu diviſo ad ſenſum compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum;
Let every mans Moderation be known to all men, all men in
ſenſu compoſito &amp; aggregato,</hi> that is, the Parliament; which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Parliament of England is, the <hi>All men of</hi>
England, &amp; now if my voice could reach to every native, and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born
of this Kingdome, my Text ſhould ring loud in their eares;
<hi>Let your Moderation</hi> in thought, word, and action be <hi>known to All
men,</hi> be ſhown to this All men, for theſe conſiderable reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, They are your ſelves, you ſent them hither, you remaine
here virtually in them, and with them, doe not vitiouſly ſuſpect, or
prejudicate their endeavours, doe not perfidiouſly, I might ſay
ſelf-feloniouſly deſert, and oppoſe them, as ſome have done; <hi>Qui
ſibi nequam, cui bonus?</hi> it is ſelf-injury and iniquitie to be injurious
to them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:112593:11"/>
Secondly, The Parliament is the ſupreame Magiſtracy of the
Kingdome, and it is a law in the Old Teſtament, not repealed in
the New, but reinforced, <hi>Exod. 22. 28. Thou ſhalt not revile the
Gods,</hi> that is, <hi>the Iudges and Governours,</hi> as the word is in the
preceding <hi>Chapter,</hi> 21. 6. and ſo it is, <hi>Act. 23. 5. Thou ſhalt not
ſpeake evill of the Ruler of thy people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, They have ſtudyed to breake off every heavy yoke,
and deliver you from that vaſſallage was brought upon you by the
tyranny of evill counſellours; Conſider well, <hi>Old Iſrael felt their
lives bitter by their cruell bondage in Egypt,</hi> Exod. 1. 14. <hi>And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
of it, they hearkened not to Moſes,</hi> Exod. 6. 9. Such a ſpirit
of bondage was upon you, you cryed for a Parliament, God heard
you, and will you now murmure againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> and fight againſt
your Deliverers?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, All the evill that is come upon you, and the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
is from your ſelves, in this very particular, ſome groane un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
burdenous taxations, in other places the warre and plunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
devoure all in a grievous and bloody manner; the former
would not have been, the other could not have been done, if you
had been true to your ſelves, and <hi>your moderation known,</hi> and
ſhown to this <hi>All men,</hi> and in them to your own peace and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, And yet let it be ſo manifeſted, becauſe the <hi>odium,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy
and danger, that is upon them from their oppoſites, is for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring
your good; let them therefore have your prayers,
your purſes, your perſons, your power, becauſe their perill is from
their <hi>Moderation;</hi> they would confine and regulate the evill coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels
about the King in Religious and Civill affaires, this is, and hath
been their great offence, which is indeed their praiſe, and I ſhall
ſpeake to them, as I ſay it of them elſewhere, they are ready to
embrace any <hi>Moderation,</hi> that is conſiſtent with the ſafetie of
Religion, King, and Kingdome.</p>
            <p>And now Worthy Senators,<note place="margin">2.</note> I beſeech you, ſuffer ye alſo a
word of Exhortation; Gods truths, you know, are above, beyond
mans power, one Nation preſumes not to give Lawes to another,
and if all the Nations in the world were conveened in an Occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menicall
Aſſembly, they ſhould have no Authoritie to moderate
any one Doctrine of the moſt High; there be ſome circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112593:11"/>
concerning which my Text ſpeaks to you; <hi>Let your Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
be known unto all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Modus regendi.</note> In the manner of enforcing them; fierce and furious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution
even of a good cauſe, is rather prejudice, then promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
but <hi>Eckius</hi> told <hi>Melancthon</hi> as it was,<note place="margin">Tua Philippe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; Pontani <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> plurimum ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juverunt cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam vestram. Vit. Melanct. pag. 335. per M. Ada.</note> that his <hi>Modeartion,</hi>
and the faire language of <hi>Pontanus,</hi> did exceedingly further them;
when <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw the Samaritans would not receive
Chriſt; <hi>they ſaid, Lord wilt thou that we command fire to come
down from heaven, and conſume them as Elias did? but he turned,
and rebuked them, and ſaid, Ye know not what manner of ſpirit ye are
of, Luk.</hi> 9. 54, 55. We muſt verily even tenaciouſly adhere to all
divine truths our ſelves, and with our wiſeſt <hi>Moderation</hi> labour
to plant, and propagate them in others, and I would ſay with
<hi>Eraſmus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ep. l. 6. p. 258.</note> 
               <hi>Mihi videtur plus profici civili modeſtia, quam impetu;</hi>
Oppoſites, indeed, muſt be oppoſed, gain-ſayed, reclaimed, but
all muſt be done in a way, and by the meanes appointed from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;
It is one thing to ſhew moderation to pious, peaceable, and
tender conſciences; it is another thing to proclaime before-hand
toleration to impious, fiery, and unpeaceable opinions: I ſay no
more, but, <hi>Sic vigilet Moderatio, ut non dormiat diſciplina;</hi> Let
Moderation be ſo much awake, that diſcipline fall not aſleep.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Sacrilegium.</note> Give me leave in the next place, to minde you of
the Harpies of this Age, who ſpying a great alteration like to be
made in the revenues of the Church, have their mouthes open,
and their fingers itch for a ſhare; here is great need of your Vm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pirage,
<hi>and Moderation:</hi> conſider, I beſeech you, there be many
darke corners in the Land, that have not where with to get oyle
for their lamps, their ſoules cry aloud for your help, and ſome aske
no more but their own, which hath too long been kept from them,
and it is now high time to make reſtitution; Sacriledge hath ever
proved a fatall offence, you will not ſo much as in purpoſe be defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
with it; you would not have Miniſters medle with ſeculari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
povertie will make them more ſecular, and if Preachers be
poore, there will be poore Preaching too at the laſt; Oh that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
Lampe in the Kingdome had its proportionable oyle, that is
your endeavour, and as you have no thought your ſelves to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle
your own Patrimonies with the Churches poſſeſſions, I
wiſh you would declare to the world, you will not ſuffer others
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112593:12"/>
to doe it; And again, I beſeech you in this; <hi>Let your Moderation
be known,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>3.<note place="margin">Templa.</note> And the fabricks of the Churches in ſome places call for
your care, the ſtone out of the wall, and the beame out of the
timber decaying apace: I am glad for my part, <hi>they are ſcoured of
their gay gazing,</hi> and I marvelled a great while ſince, how, and
why the Organs grew ſo many, and blew ſo loud, <hi>when the very
Homilies accuſed them for defiling Gods houſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Part 2. 131.</note> Much diſpute there
was of late about adherent and inherent holineſſe of Churches,
and it was accounted a ſinne to be covered in them, and it is now a
pnniſhment in ſome not to be covered, a puniſhment by the
winde and weather, from the roofe, and windowes; ſo eaſily men
fall from one extreame to another, and tis meet that in this alſo
your <hi>Moderation ſhould be knowne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dies feſti.</note>
            </p>
            <p>4. And your Moderation muſt have influence upon Holy dayes
alſo; the Lords day indeed, the holy Sabbath, is a <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi>
you muſt not otherwiſe meddle therewith, then to ſanctifie it
your ſelves, and command that by all others it be ſanctified, and in
this you doe well to uſe all diligence, becauſe of the moſt profane
and deſperate attempts of late made againſt it, as if we had beene
Turkes or Pagans,<note place="margin">De C. B. l. 16. c. 32.</note> and not Chriſtians, from Chriſt; <hi>Divino praecepto
intonante obediendum eſt, non diſputandum, Auguſtin.</hi> the thunder
of Gods word was not heard, and now the thunder of Gods
ſword is felt;<note place="margin">Immodicam fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorum multitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem non ego ſolus improbo, praeſcrum, quia hodie nullis diebus plus pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetur, quam fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis; moderata feſta valde pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ſed ea velim ſacris rebus, non voluptatibus &amp; ſceleribus dari. Io. Long Epiſc. Lincoln. l. 22. p. 914. De B. Philogon.</note> you have power, tis moſt happily improved for the
Lord, and the day of the Lord; there is reaſon and religion your
<hi>Moderation</hi> ſhould be knowne and ſhowne to the other feſtivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
not onely becauſe of their abuſe, ſuperſtition, and other evills,
but of their increaſe, the holy weeke of Lent crept into the rubri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated
Kalendar in theſe dayes: ſo did the Converſion of <hi>Paul</hi> and
<hi>Barnabas</hi> his day. I would commend the zealots of this devotion
to the care of Rome heathen, <hi>C. Caſſi: de Moderatione feſtorum,</hi>
or els to their owne <hi>Lyndwood,</hi> or above them both to <hi>Eraſmus;</hi>
for I haſten to make mention of that which I know every one ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves,
that the providence of heaven is here become a Moderator,
appointing the higheſt Feſtivitie of all the yeere, to meet with
our monthly Faſt, and be ſubdued by it: for <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> doth well
call the day of Chriſts Nativitie <hi>the Metropolis</hi> and chiefe of all
other feſtivalls; for indeed from this aroſe all the other dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:112593:12"/>
in the name of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, which els had not been
knowne in the world, thoſe be the children of that mother, and
who is not abundantly ſatisfied with the hand of God upon them
altogether, which hath, as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaid of the Iewes ſynagogue, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
them an honourable buriall? but to thoſe that are not thus ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied,
I have three other things to ſay.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Tis probable enough, we never yet kept right the day of
Chriſts Nativitie,<note place="margin">Wolf. de T. p. 81.</note> I do not meane in reſpect of the manner, but the
time, learned men ſuppoſing it very unlikely that ſuch a generall
taxation ſhould be made through the peaceable world in the
depth of winter, ſo unſeaſonable a time for all to travell into <hi>their
owne Cities to be taxed, as in Luke 2. 1. &amp;c.</hi> not to mention their
other conjectures.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Scromat. l. 1. m. p. 98.</note> 
               <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> about 1400. yeeres ſince de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares,
that ſome thought the day of Chriſts birth was in the month
of <hi>May,</hi> and others in <hi>Ianuary,</hi> others yet in <hi>Aprill;</hi> there were
yet further ſurmiſings: but obſerve, if there was ſo little certainty
in thoſe dayes, ſo neer the times of the Apoſtles, there muſt needs
be much more uncertainty now.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">Epiſt. l. 9. 71.</note> It was <hi>Gregories</hi> counſell, that the Pagan feaſts ſhould
by degrees be changed into Chriſtian Holy-dayes, that they might
the more eaſily be drawne to Chriſtianitie; and ſome write expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
that our Chriſtmas Feſtivities, in reſpect of time and maner of
celebration,<note place="margin">Io. Beleth. c 120. Hoſpin. de Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis Chriſtianis. p. 111.</note> came from the Saturnals of the Gentiles; Theſe were
alſo obſerved in the month of <hi>December,</hi> They had their liberall
Feaſtings and Invitations, ServantS among them alſo at that time
were Maſterly and followed their owne affairs, They had a wilde
Ceremony, like to the Lord of Miſrule in ſome places, New-yeers
gifts were alſo ſent abroad, which <hi>Hierome</hi> calls <hi>Saturnalium ſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulas.</hi>
But it will be ſaid,<note place="margin">Object.</note> this is hard doctrine for ſervants, whoſe
condition ſhall be worſe then beaſts, if they have no reſt, nor relax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,
and ſhall thoſe abuſes quite aboliſh the memory of Chriſts
Birth and Nativitie, and that among Chriſtians? Is this your <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration?</hi>
this reliſheth ſurely of extreame exceſſe rather.<note place="margin">R.</note> I have
three things to ſpeake againſt this pretence, not doubting, but that
ſervants ſhall have time allotted them for their refreſhing, and yet
God not robbed of his honour, care being taken that their ſports
be not ſinfull, nor they in them; and if any Sermon or Lecture oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſionally
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:112593:13"/>
be in the place, and on the day of their refreſhings, that
they repaire thither alſo, for even the Canons of 1604. required
Schoolemaſters to bring their Schollers to the Sermons, ſee them
quietly and civilly behave themſelves there, and examine them
at times convenient what they have learned by ſuch comming<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
Yea their condition then both inwardly and outwardly will
bee much bettered.<note place="margin">Can. 79.</note> And to the other part of the Objection
I ſay;</p>
            <p>Firſt, I wiſh on mine owne behalfe and others, that thoſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh,
mad, and riotous uſages had never been knowne among
Chriſtians, and that now they might be quite abandoned for ever;
but let the neighbour-hood, and charity of thoſe times at leaſt
in ſome time of the yeere be continued; ſure I am, that ſome
who had withered hands all the yeere beſide, did at that ſeaſon
ſtretch them out to the poore.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Though this day of Chriſts Birth be thus overcome
by our monethly Faſt, yet our Saviours Nativitie hath, and ſhall
have its Commemoration, not onely in the Day ſolemnized for
his Reſurrection, in which is involved all the Complement and
Conſummation of Chriſts doing and ſuffering, and Exaltation; but
further, the Lords Day is thought to be the very determinate Day
of the weeke when Chriſt was borne; for thoſe that mention the
Priviledges of the elder Brother, the firſt Day of the weeke, ſay
it was not onely the firſt Day of the world, no night went before
it,<note place="margin">Alb. M. Comp. p. 158.</note> but it ſhall be the laſt day, and no night ſhall come after it, and
that it was the very Day of Chriſts Birth and Baptiſme, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If the ſerious diſquiſition of Hiſtorians, and Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,
ſhall calculate and deſigne the moneth &amp; the day, I ſhall not
vote againſt the Chriſtian celebration therof, but as at Berne, when
the Goſpel was firſt reintroduced, they ſet their priſoners at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
and proclaimed freedome; and we obſerve a Day in memory
of our Deliverance from that Helliſh, Romiſh Powder Plot; ſo, if
God pleaſe to deliver us from the Diabolicall deſignes of theſe
times, I hope you will appoint a Day in Commemoration thereof.</p>
            <p>Fifthly,<note place="margin">Jejunia.</note> And for Faſting Dayes, your Chriſtian <hi>Moderation</hi> is
already made <hi>known,</hi> not twice or thrice in the weeke, which they
ſaid of old might ſavour of vain-glory,<note place="margin">Vit. Pat. part. 2. p. 150. 4.</note> neither have you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
ſuch rigourous obſervation, as <hi>Luther</hi> blamed in <hi>Melanct.</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:112593:13"/>
macerating his body,<note place="margin">Vit. ubi ſup.</note> 
               <hi>quaſi ferrum, aut ſaxum eſſet;</hi> nor as <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi>
who confeſſed he did too much debilitate his body by abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence,
and watching, but as <hi>Zach.</hi> 8. 19. The Faſt of the fourth
moneth, &amp;c. and yet beſides this, you have had many other occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionall
dayes of Humiliation, that which you had the laſt weeke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
your ſelves, was moſt remarkable among men, and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
we are aſſured, unto your God alſo, and yet I crave leave to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite
unto one Solemn Faſt more: Oh that a Trumpet were blown
in Sion, and a Faſt ſanctified; but I would have it ſanctified, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
both the Armies, in all the Kingdome, and though your pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
reach not ſo farre, I wiſh it were tendered to them; and triall
were made of them; however, two moſt memorable occaſions
implore Divine direction and bleſſing upon your unwearied la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Treatie of Pacification, is in your ſerious endeavours, that
the Kingdoms may yet be happy in a <hi>ſafe and well-grounded Peace;</hi>
&amp; it is high time to haſten it, the whole Land almoſt is already laid
waſte by the Sword, which, if not ſpeedily ſheathed, is bringing
upon us a worſe evill unavoydably, a Famine; for <hi>they that be ſlain
with the ſword, are better then they that be ſlain with hunger,</hi> &amp;c.
<hi>Lam.</hi> 4. 9. but let not the feare of Sword, or Famine ſcare you
into any other Peace then that which is the Peace of God made
in Chriſt, joyned with truth, elſe a greater miſchiefe will fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the Nation, then warre or hunger; <hi>Not a famine of bread, or
a thirſt for water, but of hearing the word of God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Amos</hi> 8. 11.
Great cauſe have we therefore now to cry mightily unto God, and
<hi>ſeeke of him a right way for us, and for our little ones, and for all our
ſubſtance, Ezr.</hi> 8. 21.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The great change in Eccleſiaſticals, that is to appeare
ſuddenly in the Kingdome, in reſpect of Worſhip and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
may well double our devotions in this very time;<note place="margin">Prolog. in Matth.</note> 
               <hi>Hierome</hi>
Writes, that when <hi>Cerinthus, Ebion,</hi> and other heretiques, denyed
Chriſts coming in the fleſh, the holy men of thoſe times deſired
Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> the Evangeliſt, to write his Goſpel in their confutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
which he promiſed, upon their undertaking to Faſt, and Pray
for Gods bleſſing: which done, Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> he ſaid, was full of the
holy Ghoſt, and wrote; <hi>In the beginning was the Word,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Joh.</hi>
1. 1. And indeed when the greatneſſe of this worke is looked
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:112593:14"/>
upon, with the multitude of oppoſers, there is great reaſon we
ſhould all with our holieſt diligence invocate the Majeſtie of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
that theſe things may tend to his glory, and finde acceptation
in the ſouls, hearts, and lives of the people.</p>
            <p>Sixthly,<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtici.</note> The men of my Profeſſion deſire to have a ſhare in
your <hi>Moderation</hi> alſo; and indeed I cannot think, but that of <hi>Titus,</hi>
otherwhere called,<note place="margin">Joſeph. de B. J. 7. lib. c. 13.</note> 
               <hi>deliciae humani generis,</hi> favoured not of huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,
when his ſouldiers had taken the Temple at Hieruſalem, and
the Prieſts begged their lives, he denyed them, ſaying, they ſhould
periſh together; I wiſh all the evils of theſe men were deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
but doe none of their perſons deſerve favour? did none of
them, to their power, withſtand the inundation of ſuperſtition?
When the Monks and Nunnes here thruſt themſelves out of their
unclean Cages; they had ſalaries for their lives, and in other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys,
<hi>Exire poterunt ad laborem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mycou. Vit. Zuingli.</note> 
               <hi>coniugium, literas, quis erat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimus,</hi>
They were diſmiſſed from their employment, but had ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends
to their death: You have already herein declared your <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration,</hi>
in aſſigning a portion, for the ſupport of wife, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
and it were well, if no complaints were brought before you
againſt ſome, that are ſo loath to part there with.</p>
            <p>Seventhly,<note place="margin">Heterodoxi.</note> Another ſort of men call for your <hi>Moderation;</hi> yea,
and plead merit too; I know not what to call them, but I meane
the men of many opinions, though, I hope, they be neither ſo nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous,
nor faultie, as their oppoſites ſuggeſt, and yet to as many
of them, as pretend to godlineſſe, and be with us in Covenant, I
ſay no more, but wiſh them to read it, to ſtudy it, to keep it; in the
reſt, I would wonder with what conſcience, or wiſdome they
abſtaine from that bond, when the Romaniſts univerſally are in
armed combination againſt them, and us; a very hard matter, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe,
it is to moderate erroneous opinions, ſome have dared into
the world that ſhould have been, Anonyma, not once named as
becometh Saints; and for the reſt, I thought ſometimes, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
me, if I thinke ſo ſtill, if their <hi>Tenents</hi> were commanded
from them, in expreſſe termes, they would appeare, either not to
be <hi>tanti,</hi> that for them publique tranquillitie ſhould be endangered,
or elſe coming forth naked into the world, barefaced, and in their
colours, they would be a ſhame to their abbettors.</p>
            <p>Eightly,<note place="margin">Papifts.</note> The Papiſts indeed, that be Ieſuited, in reſpect of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:112593:14"/>
their guilt, and <hi>Irelands</hi> bloud, expect not your <hi>Moderation;</hi> and
ſurely ſuch ſhould be ſhowne them, as may preſerve your ſelves
and the Kingdomes from their frauds and cruelties; againſt which
you will be now more vigilant then ever, becauſe they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed
now more then ever their evill intentions, and can ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
thoſe oathes without chewing, which former times of peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſſe
could not get downe, by any art or perſwaſion: and
though their very Religion,<note place="margin">p. 503.</note> like <hi>Draco's</hi> Lawes, be written in
bloud, as King <hi>Iames</hi> obſerved: and in the Nether-lands they
made a ſhew of <hi>Moderation,</hi> and called their Edict ſo, yet even
that in truth was, was felt, and was then called <hi>Murderation;</hi> alſo as
<hi>Meterane</hi> writes,<note place="margin">p. 46</note> they had then their <hi>Conſilium ſanguinis:</hi> they
walke by the ſame Principles, and worſe Practiſes; yet none
of them ever ſuffered death among us meerely for Religion. [I
had other particulars to have mentioned, but I ſaw the time would
not permit me to ſpeak them out of the Pulpit; I forbeare them
therefore now alſo;<note place="margin">Secunda par. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>] and I come to handle the reaſon of the Text,
but Doctrinally, and very briefly: <hi>The Lord is at hand:</hi> and I ſhall
not inſiſt upon the Lords being at hand, by his providentiall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proximation
to ſupport us in, or deliver us from trouble, as <hi>Pſal.</hi>
22. 11. <hi>Be not farre from me, O Lord, for trouble is neere:</hi> nor
how <hi>he is at hand</hi> to obſerve all our actions, ſo keeping us in awe
and obedience, becauſe <hi>All things are naked, and opened to the eyes
of him with whom we have to doe,</hi> Heb. 4. 13. But in this Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
part of the propinquitie of our Lords coming to judgement,
I ſhall ſhew firſt, the parallel Scriptures; and ſecondly, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable
reaſons thence; and then the Application will be in ſuch
practicall uſes as you ſhall ſee Gods Word hold forth viſibly in
thoſe places where the Text, or the ſenſe of it, is mentioned.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Scripture.</note> It is very conſiderable that the Apoſtles all ſo ſpeake, as if
Chriſt, the Lord, would in their dayes come to judgement, ſo
many hundred years agoe. Thus 1 <hi>Cor. 10. 11. We are they upon
whom the ends of the world are come.</hi> So <hi>Heb. 10. 37. Yet a little while,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>yet a very very little while, and he that ſhall come,
will come, and will not tarry.</hi> And Saint <hi>Iames 3. Behold, the Iudge
ſtandeth before the doore,</hi> 5. 9. And Saint <hi>Peter, The end of all things
is at hand:</hi> And thus Saint <hi>Iohn, It is the laſt time, 1 Ioh.</hi> 2. 18. And
ſo Saint <hi>Iude,</hi> 18. And if ſo then a thouſand years agoe, it is the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:112593:15"/>
miracle of miracles, that yet the Lord is not come to judgement:
the ſucceeding Ages after the Apoſtles were of the ſame mind,
and they watched on Eaſter Even by ancient tradition, as if their
Maſter Chriſt would in one of thoſe Vigils come to judge
the world; <hi>in ſimilitudinem Aegyptii temporis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian:
As Pharaoh the King roſe up in the night,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 107. <hi>K.</hi> Lactan. 7. 19. Hieron. in <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. Auguſt. de T. 154. 251. De Vn. Eccl. p. 301.</note> 
               <hi>and all his ſervants, and
there was a great cry in Egypt, &amp;c.</hi> Exod. 12. 30. And in <hi>Cyprians</hi>
time all things were accompliſhed, as he thought, that were
forerunning tokens of the worlds end. It were eaſie to heape up
the conjectures of ſeverall Centuries; but we muſt all acquieſce
in the determination of our Maſter who ſhall be the Iudge, <hi>Matt.</hi>
24. 36. <hi>Of that day and houre knoweth no man, no not the Angels of
heaven, but the Father onely.</hi> But that I may prepare my ſelfe
and you to the ſerious and practicall conſideration of the fore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
Vſes: obſerve theſe Scripture arguments.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Reaſons.</note> 
               <hi>There ſhall be ſignes in the Sunne, and the Moone, &amp;c.
Luk.</hi> 21. 25. And if Mathematicians, may be credited, the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall
Orbes are not as they were:<note place="margin">Aret. Probl. p. 1016.</note> the Sunne not ſo diſtant from
us as at the firſt, but nearer by many Germane miles; to ſay
nothing of the prodigious ſights and noiſes ſeene and heard in our
dayes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Mens hearts faile them for feare, &amp;c.</hi> Luk. 21. 26<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
As lightning is firſt ſeene, then thunder heard; ſmoke precedes
fire, and the ſea ſwels before a ſtorme; ſo the ſoule of man, that
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Epiſt.</note> as <hi>Syneſius,</hi> cals it, droops before danger, trembles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
it is hurt, and by its inward timorouſneſſe foretels evils to
come; and that appeares by the ſeverall preſagings of men that
diſcover their feares by their conjectures: That famous <hi>Grebner</hi>
found out the yeare of the worlds end by the word <hi>Iudicium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DICI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M numerum rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turi continet orbis. Problem. p. 1057. Ecce Sponſ. ven.</note> eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
letter thereof being numerall; but we have already outlived
that fancie above thirty years. <hi>Aretius</hi> by ſome Chronogramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall
expreſſions of Scripture, propoſed this next to be the laſt
yeare of the world. Doctor <hi>Alabaſters</hi> conceit out of thoſe two
Greeke words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, may ſavour of fancy and feare.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Religion and Holineſſe, the two pillars of Heaven and
Earth, are ſo much decayed and diſcountenanced, as we need no
other demonſtration that <hi>thoſe laſt and perillous times</hi> are come,
that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake of, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 1. For as the old age of man,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:112593:15"/>
the leſſer world, is full of corporall infirmities; ſo the greater
world in its declining eſtate abounds with manifold abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:
read at leaſure the two next verſes, and ſee how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily
theſe dayes comment upon them; if you thinke on any
one of thoſe ſinnes, the ſame thought will tell you where to find
them.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The unnaturall diviſions that are up in the world, are
undenyable preſages that the <hi>Lord is at hand:</hi> for when the
Diſciples privately demanded of their Maſter, what ſhould be the
ſignes of his coming to judgement; among others this is recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
by the three Evangeliſts: <hi>The brother ſhall betray the brother
to death, and the father the ſonne, &amp;c.</hi> Mar. 13. 12. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. 10.
<hi>Luk.</hi> 21. 16. And we need not enquire among Iewes, Turkes,
and other Nations for the accompliſhment hereof; but as Chriſt
in another caſe, <hi>Luk.</hi> 4. 21. I may ſay, <hi>This day is this Scripture
fulfilled in your cares,</hi> O <hi>England:</hi> never ſince thou wert a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
didſt thou ſee thy ſelfe ſo miſerably torne, and rent with ſuch
civill, uncivill, unnaturall, and bloudy diſtractions: If it had beene
ſaid to any of thy people, foure or five yeares ſince, that they
ſhould doe ſuch things, as are now done in the midſt of thee; they
would have replied with the indignation of <hi>Hazael, 2. King.</hi> 8. 13.
<hi>Are we dogges,</hi> deſtitute of all humanity, <hi>to doe this?</hi> and yet,
wretched things are done by men, Chriſtian men, <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> profeſſing the ſame Religion, proteſting the
ſame Cauſe, and End of their quarrell: O that thou couldſt yet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne
thoſe formidable clouds of bloud in their ſcattering: but
alaſſe, they threaten worſer evils, even to make thee a full ſea of
bloud within, as thou art without ſurrounded by water: for the
wofull diviſions of <hi>England</hi> there be great thoughts of heart: I
will not ſay, as <hi>Ieremie 2. 12. Be ye aſtoniſhed, O heavens, at this;</hi>
Nor, <hi>be aſhamed ye Husbandmen,</hi> Ioel 1. 11. But let all thoſe be
aſhamed and aſtoniſhed, Prophets and people, that have not help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to quench, but kindle this fire: <hi>This is indeed a lamentation, and
ſhall be for a lamentation,</hi> Ezek. 19. 14. But to returne from this
ſad complaint upon our moſt miſerable diſſenſions, a dolefull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage
that <hi>the Lord is at hand,</hi> the props of the world decay; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious
ſights portend as much, and the fainting of mens hearts
fore-bode the ſame: I am not ignorant, that ſome convinced by
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:112593:16"/>
ſtrong evidence of Chriſts reigning here upon earth; before that
time, underſtand all theſe places of that coming of Chriſt; and my
purpoſe is not at all to pry into thoſe hard and hidden moments of
Gods owne concealing: and ſure I am, thoſe that wade this
way meet with deepe difficulties; as bow?</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>irſt, all the fore-named Scriptures ſhould be ſo applied,
1 Cor. 10. 11. <hi>The ends of the world are come:</hi> and it is not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
the Romane world or Empire, as <hi>Luk.</hi> 2. 1. And Saint
<hi>Peter</hi> is yet more univerſally expreſſe; <hi>The end of all things is at
hand,</hi> 1 Pet. 4. 7.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the day of judgement is called, <hi>A great and notable
day, Act. 2. 20. An appointed day,</hi> 17. 31. Yet it is more then
one, <hi>one of the dayes of the Sonne of man,</hi> Luk. 17. 22. 26.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Who can determine the finals of the Beaſts power,
unleſſe the Originals were manifeſt? <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 5, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I might ſay much of Ancient and Moderne confidences this
way, but my purpoſe is to improve the remaining time allotted,
in the ſerious conſideration of what God himſelfe tels, we ought
all practically learne from the <hi>Lords being at hand,</hi> and the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
now in the land may, and ought to haſten theſe truths home
to our ſoules.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Repentance.</note> Speedy Repentance from dead workes: reade <hi>Act.</hi> 17.
30, 31.—<hi>Now he commandeth all men every where to repent,
becauſe he hath appointed a day in which he will iudge the world, &amp;c.</hi>
Many things are here obſervable, but the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Now,</hi> is that
I deſire to faſten upon you, and my ſelfe; for if in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi>
dayes it was an argument of, and to Repentance; it ſhould much
more accelerate us thereunto, upon whom the Lord is nearer
now by ſixteene hundred yeeres. Conſider with thy ſelfe then,
O my ſoule, and ſuppoſe, thou wert here guilty of ſome capitall
crime, for which the Iudge were ready to reckon with thee, and
paſſe ſentence of death, or deliverance, as he finds thee; couldeſt
thou ſleepe or be ſecure? or wouldeſt thou trifle away thy time?
would not all thy care be by ſome meanes or other to gaine favour
from the Iudge? Be thou aſſured, O my ſoule, <hi>That the ungodly
ſhall not ſtand in the iudgement,</hi> Pſal. 1. 5. Thy conſcience knows
what a load of ſinne lies upon thee; <hi>even a burden too heavie for
thee to beare,</hi> Pſal. 38. 4. Oh why doſt thou not haſten to eaſe thy
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:112593:16"/>
ſelfe of this weight by unfained repentance, before the Iudge
come, and pronounce the irrevocable ſentence? Read, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
to doe as <hi>Act. 3. 19. Repent ye, and be converted, that your
ſinnes may be blotted out, when the times of refreſhing ſhall come from
the preſence of the Lord.</hi> Infinit is the matter of our Humiliation,
in reſpect of nature, perſons, and nation; of paſt, and preſent
times: but this day, and thoſe next it, have beene heretofore the
onely merry ſeaſon of the yeare, and the Devill hath beene ſerved
better on thoſe Twelve dayes, then on all the twelve moneths be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide;
and our Maſter Chriſt hath moſt unchriſtianly by many been
diſhonoured, even in thoſe dayes ſaid to be devoted to his glory:
And I may borrow here the words of <hi>Nicholas de Clemangis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">M. p. 143.</note>
touching his Popiſh Feſtivities; What heathen man, if he had
come into thoſe feaſts, ſeene and heard our Chriſtmas Gamboles,
would not have taken them rather to be the <hi>Floralia</hi> of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi>
or the <hi>Orgia</hi> of <hi>Bacchus,</hi> then Chriſtian holy dayes? and who
can lay his hand upon his heart, and ſay, he is innocent as touching
this in all reſpects?<note place="margin">Ordinance.</note> Great cauſe therefore had your Ordinance to
command this <hi>day to be kept with more ſolemne humiliation, becauſe
it may call to remembrance our ſinnes, and the ſinnes of our fore-fathers,
who have turned this feaſt, pretending the memory of Chriſt,
into an extreme for getfulneſſe of him, by giving libertie to carnall
and ſonſuall delights, being contrary to the life which Chriſt himſelfe
led here upon earth:</hi> Thoſe dayes were profeſſedly dedicated to
extraordinary mirth, and rejoycing: we read no ſuch thing of our
Maſter Chriſt at any time, but he wept often, <hi>and offered up many
prayers, and ſupplications with ſtrong crying and teares,</hi> Heb. 5. 7.
Our Maſter Chriſt was never idle; but <hi>went about doing good,</hi> Act.
10. 38. and elſewhere, every where in the Goſpel; but among
us it was accounted almoſt a crime, for men, or their ſervants to
doe any labour on any of thoſe dayes: practiſes, as your Ordinance
ſaid truly, <hi>contrary to the ſpirituall life of Chriſt in our ſoules, for
the ſanctifying and ſaving whereof Chriſt was pleaſed both to take
an humane life, and to lay it downe againe:</hi> but the extreme for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulneſſe
of Chriſt in thoſe dayes of Chriſt, the extreme exceſſe
of carnall and ſenſuall delights were moſt extremely diſtant from
that ſpirituall life ſhould be in Chriſtians, <hi>who worke out their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
with feare and trembling,</hi> Phil. 2. 12. not in ſecure, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:112593:17"/>
and profane merriment; <hi>They paſſe the time of their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iourning
here in feare,</hi> 1 Pet. 1. 17. Not onely becauſe he <hi>that hath
called us is holy, and bids us to be ſo likewiſe,</hi> verſ. 15. 16. but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
of our <hi>redemption by the precious bloud of Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> verſ. 18,
19. therefore we ſhould <hi>paſſe our time in feare;</hi> not in wanton,
wild, and impious paſtimes, which doe put men into a poſture
altogether unmeet for the ſervice of Chriſt, or care of our ſoules:
had the Nation no other ſinnes to anſwer for, ſurely without the
bloud of Chriſt, whom men have ſo much diſhonoured to his face,
we ſhould be in a moſt deſperate condition: Goe hence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
and examine, and bewaile, and conſider, Gods providence
hath made this day, this very day, the head of all that jocundity, a
day of Humiliation; doe not miſcall it, let it be ſo to every one of
us, for our owne, the Nationall tranſgreſſions it hath beene for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
guilty of in thoſe dayes; and if the Lord, <hi>who is at hand,</hi> had
called any of us out of the world, when we were buſie in thoſe
fooliſh, vaine, and unchriſtian uſages; we may now tremble to
thinke how unfit we had beene to meet the Lord Ieſus coming
in the clouds.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Heavenly-mindedneſſe.</note> Let us wiſely weane our ſelves from the world,
and this we learne from the very next words after the Text, <hi>The
Lord is at hand, In nothing be carefull:</hi> Yea, our Lord himſelfe
gives us the ſame counſell, in the very ſame words, <hi>Luk.</hi> 21. 34.
<hi>Take heed that your hearts be not at any time overcome with the
cares of this life, and that day come upon you unawares:</hi> There may
be a ſeaſon for other things, but none for Chriſtians to be ſollicitous
for earthly things: <hi>Our Father is in heaven, ſo we ſay, ſo we
pray; heaven is our Countrey, ſo we profeſſe,</hi> Heb. 11. 16. Why
doe we then digge ſo deepe in the earth, and deſire to load our
ſelves with thick clay? The Apoſtle, in the Chapter before my
Text, hath expreſſions that may loath any man thereof; <hi>whoſe end
is deſtruction, and their glory is in their ſhame, who mind earthly
things,</hi> Phil. 3. 19. Damnation is their end, and why ſhould not
Hell be their portion, who care not for Heaven? But they are
the brave men of the world in the meane time: No ſuch matter,
<hi>their glory is in their ſhame;</hi> they wallow in the myre with ſwine,
that might have converſed with Saints: But who are thoſe dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
and inglorious men? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, men that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:112593:17"/>
are wiſe for <hi>the world, that mind earthly things.</hi> What ſhall I ſay
more, what can I adde better, then that of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
7. 29, 30, 31. <hi>This I ſay brethren, the time is ſhort, it remaineth that
both they who have wives, be as though they had none; and they that
weepe, as though they wept not; and they that reioyce, as though
they reioyced not; and they that buy, as though they poſſeſſed not;
and they that uſe this world, as though they uſed it not; for the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion
of this world paſſeth away:</hi> The dehortation is very full and
emphaticall; but that which I eſpecially obſerve in it is, that it is
compaſſed in, and about, at the beginning, and in the end, with
the argument of my Text, leſt our hearts, that hanker ſo much
world-ward, ſhould any way get out, after it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">Perſeverance.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord is at hand,</hi> therefore conſtantly perſevere
in his holy truths, and this Vſe is held out to us by <hi>Iohn</hi> the Divine,
<hi>Bleſſed is he that readeth, and they that keep the words of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie:
for the time is at hand,</hi> Revel. 1. 3. Yea and S. <hi>Paul,</hi> aſſoon as
he had mentioned this doctrine, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 11, makes this very uſe
and application; <hi>Wherfore let him that thinketh he ſtandeth, take heed
leſt he full, ver.</hi> 12. He that is ſtrong, muſt not be ſecure, becauſe he
ſtands in ſlippery places, nay he ſtandeth not, onely <hi>he thinketh that
he ſtandeth, therfore let him take heed leſt he fall:</hi> and caution for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance
is not onely ſutable to my text, but the times, theſe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering
times, wherein men are moſt apt to recidivate, and fall
away, as the parable of the <hi>ſeed and ſowers make evident, Matth.</hi>
13. 21. <hi>Peter</hi> and the other Apoſtles promiſed fairly to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
and their Maſter in the Calme, <hi>Though wee ſhould die with
thee, yet will we not deny thee, ſo ſaid all the Diſciples, Mat.</hi> 26. 35.
Yet in the ſtorm, nay before the ſtorme came at them, they runne
away for feare, they haſte to ſhelter, indeed from ſhelter, becauſe
from Chriſt, <hi>They all forſooke him, and ſted, verſ.</hi> 56. Thus <hi>Demas</hi>
entangled with the love of earthly things, deſerts Chriſt, and his
Apoſtle, <hi>embraceth the preſent world, and departs to Theſſalonica,</hi>
2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 10. where he is made a keeper of the Pagan Idoles, as
ſome of the Ancient have recorded;<note place="margin">Doroth. Synop.</note> but as for us, let that of our
Maſter Chriſt be ever in our ears, alwayes in our hearts, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 9.
<hi>He that denieth me before men ſhall be denyed before the Angels of
God,</hi> and if Chriſt turne his face from thee in that day, tremble at
thy doome, who will, who can; who dare ſpeake for thee, if thine
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:112593:18"/>
owne Advocate be ſilent, and indeed it is moſt juſt they be ſo dealt
with, that Apoſtatize from the truths of Chriſt; it is juſt, I ſay,
<hi>Lege talionis,</hi> even by the Law of retaliation; for that's the ſentence
of the holy Ghoſt, <hi>If we deny him, he will alſo deny us,</hi> 2. Tim.
2. 12.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">Holineſſe.</note> Zealous endeavours after holineſſe: and thus S. <hi>Paul</hi>
having ſpoken of the <hi>Iudgement to come, 2 Cor.</hi> 5. 10. he adds
preſently, <hi>verſ 11. Knowing therefore the terrour of the Lord, we
perſwade men,</hi> to what? but the righteous actions of godlineſſe and
Chriſtianity: and upon this very foundation S. <hi>Peter</hi> builds a ſtrong
argument to holineſſe; for having ſpoken at large doctrinally of
the day of the Lord, as alſo concerning the formidable manner of
his coming, 2 <hi>Pet. 3. 11. Seeing then that all theſe things muſt be
diſſolved, what manner of perſons ought ye to be in all holy converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
and godlineſſe?</hi> he interrogates, but anſwers not, not becauſe
the holy Ghoſt was at a <hi>Non plus,</hi> and could not expreſſe it; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
he would have us enquire, examine, and increaſe in every
good word and worke in our own perſons, and as farre as ever our
relations doe, and can reach private men in their intereſts, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
perſons in their engagements, according to that of the holy
Prophet, which concerns every one of us, <hi>Let iudgement run
downe as waters, and righteouſneſſe as a mighty ſtream, Amos</hi> 5. 12.
It muſt be done ſpeedily, delayed no longer, <hi>let it run downe,</hi> and
it muſt be performed impartially, <hi>run down as waters,</hi> which favour
none, drench all that be neer them, yea and powerfully alſo, <hi>as a
mightie ſtream,</hi> that will ſuffer no obſtructions, but beares all oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions
before it; and that of the author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> is pertinent
to this purpoſe alſo, <hi>Let us conſider one another to provoke unto love,
and to good works, not forſaking the aſſembling of our ſelves together
as the manner of ſome is, but exhorting one another, and ſo much the
more, becauſe ye ſee the day approaching, Heb.</hi> 10. 24. 25. a Scripture
otherwiſe remarkable in theſe times, wherein men conſider one
another, and provoke not to love, but to ſchiſme, and ſiding, not to
good works, but their owne fancies, to ſeparation, <hi>and forſaking the
aſſemblies:</hi> but there the Apoſtle layes the force, and ſo would I,
in the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſo much the more</hi> provoke one another to
good works, <hi>becauſe ye ſee the day approaching.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly,<note place="margin">Patience.</note> Chriſtian Patience in tribulation, is the next thing to be
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:112593:18"/>
learned from this doctrine of the <hi>Lords being at hand;</hi> an hard leſſon
I confeſſe, and they are out of the Forme, and Schoole of nature
that have learned it, for it is an herbe of Grace, and grows not in
mans garden, we are all by <hi>nature children of wrath, Eph.</hi> 2. 3. not
onely <hi>paſſively,</hi> ſubject to ſuffer the wrath of God becauſe of our
ſinnes, but <hi>actively</hi> alſo, we are hot, fiery, and impatient, and upon
every occaſion doe diſcover our diſtemper; <hi>Luther</hi> ſpake obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly,
becauſe his own heart, God hath given us, ſaith he, many bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings,
health, quietneſſe, wife, children, and which is above all, the
word of his Patience, and yet one fit of the Stone beats out the
memory of all theſe benefits;<note place="margin">3. 59. 5. 81.</note> 
               <hi>Vno malo plus movemur quam mille
bonis,</hi> Though we have had twentie yeers of felicitie, if one day of
ſorrow come, all the former calmneſſe is forgotten, clouds of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation
gather, and breake out into ſtreames of impatience; nay,
if one tooth doe but ake, that Center or point of paine darkens
all the Sphere and circumference of Gods mercies; It were eaſie
to abound in complaining, but farre more comfortable to faſten
upon a remedy, and that is not farre of; becauſe <hi>the Lord is at
hand;</hi> and what ſenſe ſoever is put upon the words, they breath
upon us abundant matter of patience.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Lord is ſo nigh, that no ſuffering can befall us with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
his appointment, and if we remember it is his hand, we will
not utter ſo much as one word of impatience; as <hi>David</hi> profeſſed,
<hi>He was dumbe and opened not his mouth, becauſe the Lord did it,
Pſal.</hi> 39. 9.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Lords example is neere, ſhould alwayes be at
hand for our animation and encouragement; <hi>It is enough for the
diſciple to be as his Maſter, and the ſervant as his Lord, Matth.</hi> 10.
25. an expreſſion that may make us not onely patient, but joyfull,
yea triumphant in miſery, Chriſtians to be as their Maſter Chriſt, it
is enough, and they that conſider it well, need no other conſolation.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Scriptures of Chriſt are <hi>written for our comfort,
Rom.</hi> 15. 4. and in them the Lord is at hand; <hi>For the word is neere
thee,</hi> even <hi>in thy mouth, and in thy heart, Rom.</hi> 10. 8. and for this, in
this, thou mayeſt be patient; <hi>I will reioyce in him</hi> becauſe of his
<hi>word, in the Lord I will reioyce</hi> becauſe of his word, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 56. 10.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Yea the Lord is at hand, to put a period to all our
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:112593:19"/>
preſſures; <hi>Looke up, and lift up your heads, for the day of your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption
draweth nigh,</hi> Luk. 21. 28. ſo Iam. 5. 7, 8. <hi>Be patient
therefore brethren, unto the coming of the Lord; Behold, the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman
waiteth for the precious fruit of the earth, and hath long
patience for it, till he receive the early and latter raine; be ye alſo
patient, ſtabliſh your hearts, for the coming of the Lord draweth
nigh;</hi> It is no great matter that the husbandman expects, <hi>fruit
of the earth, yet he hath great patience;</hi> we have much more in
hope, heavenly and eternall things: and therefore we ſhould be
much more in patience, and we may note alſo the reaſon of the
Text, begins and ends, compaſſeth about this leſſon of patience;
<hi>initio 7. verſ. &amp; fine</hi> 8. Yea in this, and for this, heare the Iudge
himſelf, <hi>who is at hand,</hi> Luk. 21. 19. <hi>By your patience poſſeſſe your
ſoules,</hi> a direction for times like ours, ſuffering times, <hi>ye ſhall be ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
of all men for my names ſake,</hi> Verſ. 17. and if they ſay, Maſter,
in that deplorable condition, where no man will appeare for us,
what ſhall we do?<note place="margin">Non villas ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtras, non laudes, non luxurias. Auguſt. <hi>Faith.</hi>
               </note> his anſwer is, be not ſolicitous for your houſes,
or lands, or reputation, or body, but for your ſoules; <hi>poſſeſſe them
by patience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, Faith in the Lord Ieſus Chriſt is alſo commended to us,
from this Doctrin of the <hi>Lords being at hand,</hi> for when the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
had ſaid, <hi>Heb. 10. 37. Yet a very little while, and he that ſhall
come, will come, and will not tarry;</hi> every one that heares this, and
believes it, would preſently make enquiry, Is the Iudge com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
ſo certainly, ſo ſpeedily, ſo ſuddenly? and is he indeed <hi>ſo nigh
at hand?</hi> Alas, what ſhall we then doe, what courſe ſhall we take,
where, or how ſhall we appeare? The anſwer is ready, moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
and comfortable, in the very next words, <hi>Verſ. 38. Now
the iuſt ſhall live by faith; Now,</hi> at that very time, in the inſtant of
Chriſts judging the world, faith ſhall ſupport and uphold all that
depend upon God: A man indebted, that hath not where with to
ſatisfie his Creditor, dares not looke him in the face; but if his
Suretie take out the Bond, all is well, and he is ſafe: We are all
runne into deep arreares with, and againſt God by our ſinnes, and
cannot <hi>anſwer him one thing of a thouſand, Iob</hi> 9. 3. not the leaſt
part of one of many thouſands, what ſhall we then doe? Live by
faith, and our intereſt in the price of Chriſts blood, pay all the debt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:112593:19"/>
of our ungodlineſſe, that great and ſuperabundant expiation is
made over to us by holy beleeving; for he was not onely <hi>our Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
Heb.</hi> 7. 22. but he hath <hi>blotted out the hand-writing that was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
us, and taken it out of the way,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 14. It is written
of <hi>Pilate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">M. Weſt. ad A. 38.</note> that being call'd to Rome before the Emperour, to give
account of ſome Mal-adminiſtration, and miſgovernment, he put
on the ſeamleſſe Coat of Chriſt, and all the time he ware that gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<hi>Caeſars</hi> fury was abated, to his own, and others admiration;
That may be a Fable: but ſure I am, if we have the Robes of
Chriſts Righteouſneſſe upon us by a lively faith, we ſhall then
have no cauſe of feare, in that we have not onely <hi>an Advocate
with the Father, 1 Ioh.</hi> 7. 2. but Chriſt the Iudge, for our defence
and deliverance; It is a terrible queſtion, that of <hi>Iob,</hi> but very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable;
and oh my ſoule ſleep not this night, nor any other till thou
haſt put it home to thy ſelfe; <hi>For the Lord is at hand;</hi> the queſtion
is, <hi>What ſhall I doe, when God riſeth up, and when he viſiteth, what
ſhall I anſwer him? Iob</hi> 31. 14. To which no other anſwer, no
better anſwer can be given, then that of Saint <hi>Paul. Rom</hi> 13. 14.
<hi>Put on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and make not proviſion for the fleſh, to
fulfill the luſts thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly,<note place="margin">Prayer.</note> The laſt Practicall conſideration held ſorth from this
Doctrine of the <hi>Lords being nigh at hand,</hi> is ſober watchfulneſſe
unto prayer, and this is the very Vſe, in termes, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> wils
us to make thereof, who having ſaid; <hi>The end of all things is at
hand;</hi> addeth this immediate inference: <hi>Be you therefore ſober,
and watch unto prayer, 1 Pet.</hi> 4. 7. Yea, our Lord himſelfe, <hi>who is a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
hand,</hi> ſpeaks to each of theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, Concerning</hi> Sobrietie; Take heed, leſt at any time your
hearts be overcome with ſurfetting and drunkenneſſe, and that day
come on you unaw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>res, <hi>Luk.</hi> 21. 34.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Evangeliſts generally, for the ſame reaſon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort
to <hi>watching, Matth. 24. 42. Mark.</hi> 13. 33. and they doe not
meane ſo much abſtinence from ſleep, but from ſinne, and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
not for worldlineſſe, but for prayer.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, So, <hi>Luke 21. 36. Watch ye therefore, and pray alwayes:</hi>
and in the next words, he gives a <hi>Directory of Prayer,</hi> two heads
of petitions, one, <hi>That ye may be accounted worthy to eſcape all theſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:112593:20"/>
things that ſhall come to paſſe;</hi> the other, <hi>that ye may ſtand before
the Sonne of man;</hi> and if you aske when, and how often this muſt
be remembred, he tels us that alſo; <hi>pray alwayes:</hi> a dutie needfull
ever, but moſt of all now, in reſpect of our own particulars, and the
Churches of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And for our ſelves, let us pray for pardon of ſin, ſtrength againſt
luſts, ſtanding in judgement; and as the Martyrs in priſon, and at
the ſtake, ſaid to themſelves, and others; Pray, pray, pray: ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<hi>the Lord is at hand;</hi> therefore forget not to pray, yea,
<hi>Watch, and pray,</hi> Matth. 26. 41. <hi>that ye enter not into tentations,</hi> into
the devouring part thereof,<note place="margin">Ne intremus in ventr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m tentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis, quaſi beſtiae cujuſdam. Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phylact.</note> as the belly of a beaſt: we know not
what calamitous times may be reſerved for us, but whatſoever
they are, or may be, we cannot be armed againſt them, but by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
ſo we muſt be prepared, and this we ſee by our Apoſtle, who
to the Text, <hi>The Lord is at hand,</hi> inſtantly ſubjoynes; <hi>Be carefull
for nothing, but in every thing by prayer and ſupplication with
thanks giving, let your requeſt be made known unto God, Phil.</hi> 4. 6.
Pray for me, ſaith Father <hi>Latimer</hi> to Biſhop <hi>Ridley,</hi> again and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain
pray for me,<note place="margin">p. 14.</note> for I am ſometimes ſo fearefull, that I could
creepe into a Mouſehole; (It is his own expreſſion) but God doth
viſit me again with his conſolation: and then the other anſwers
him, unleſſe the Lord aſſiſts me with his gracious ayde in the time
of his ſervice, <hi>I know I ſhall play but the part of a white-liver'd
Knight;</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 15.</note> and yet what Champions, what victorious Champions
were they both; and that by prayer? For in the ſame little Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe
of their comfortable conference, during the time of their
impriſonment, <hi>Ridley</hi> calles on <hi>Latimer,</hi> as upon an <hi>Old beaten
Souldier for inſtruction,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 16.</note> 
               <hi>and help to buckle on his harneſſe;</hi> as he
phraſeth it: and <hi>Latimer</hi> tels him, <hi>you ſhall prevaile more with pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
then ſtudying,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 36.</note> 
               <hi>though mixture be beſt;</hi> but forget not to pray.
Let every one for our ſelves remember, <hi>the Lord is at hand;</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,
the houſes we dwell in are made of clay, and the calamities
of theſe times are daily battering theſe Tabernacles of duſt, that
may very ſoone, and ſuddenly fall about our eares; therefore let
every one of us alwayes <hi>be ſober and watchfull unto prayer,</hi> and
pray earneſtly to God, that he will give us Repentance from dead
works, that he will weane us from theſe things below, and teach
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:112593:20"/>
us to perſevere in all Divine truth, and make us abound in every
good word and worke, that he will enable us to be patient in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation,
and fill us with the moſt holy faith in the Lord Ieſus
Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And for the Churches of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Jer. 30. 7.</note> remember it is their Day, <hi>the
very day of Jacobs trouble;</hi> all the Iſrael of our God is in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexitie,
pray for them all, at home and abroad, pray for the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw
of Antichriſt, the fall of Babylon; pray for the Peace of
Hieruſalem, and the wellfare of Sion; yea, pray earneſtly, holily,
conſtantly,<note place="margin">Gen. 32. 26.</note> and as <hi>Iacob, wraſtle with God, and doe not let him goe,
till he give you a bleſſing; And you that make mention of the Lord,
hold not your peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 62. 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>day nor night, keep not ſilence, and give him no reſt,
till he eſtabliſh, and till he make Hieruſalem,</hi> the Churches abroad,
and in theſe Kingdomes, <hi>a praiſe in the earth.</hi> And let us of this
Nation pray, pray that God would returne the Head to the Body,
the King to the Parliament; that he will heale our breaches, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
our differences, and haſten the reſtauration of a ſafe and well
grounded Peace, that yet ſticks in the Birth; pray that he would lift
up the light of his countenance upon England, Scotland, and Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.
<hi>Lord, lift up the light of thy countenance upon them, and they
ſhall be ſafe;</hi> And let all them that love God, that love their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
that love their Countrey; that love their Souls, ſay Amen; Yea,
ſay thou Amen to theſe things; Thou that Art <hi>the Amen,
the faithfull and true Witneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 3.—14.</note> 
               <hi>the beginning of
the Creation of God.</hi> Amen, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
